Hello everyone, welcome to this video.
In this video, we will be discussing
about model context protocol also widely
known as MCP. It acts like a universal
adapter for AI. We all know that LLM
cannot perform anything without tools.
Let's say you have a tool implementation
that works for GPT. However, there is no
guarantee that the same implementation
will work for Germany or Deepseek.
So MCP what it does is that it
standardize the implementation. So
whenever you use the MCP to do your
tooling implementation
you can connect with any other LLM.
Let's assume that I have three different
tool implementation maybe like this one
for Google Drive, YouTube and this is
for something else. So right now like in
my organization I'm using GPT. So I can
connect with using the MCP with all the
tools. So tomorrow I don't want to use
uh GPT rather like I wanted to use a gin
I don't have to make any changes I just
connect with the MCP then you know start
using all these tool and day after
tomorrow I wanted to use deepseek just
as he says that just uh remove these and
like use this connect with that let's
you know start using the tool so that
way it's kind of a universal adapter you
can you know remove anything add
anything at any time without any effort
required for the integration. If you are
coming from a net or a Java background,
you may be wondering like why do I need
another standard like I already have a
open API standard. So let's see like
what is the difference between the open
API specification and the MCP. So open
API it's meant for operation. Let's say
like you want to add something or
retrieve something at the time you will
be creating the individual operations
get, post, patch, delete or whatever is
for each operation you will be creating
a endpoint. However, LLM are not for
operation rather it is task oriented.
You want to complete a task you have to
create a task oriented implementation
not necessarily the operation. So
basically the difference is that the
task can have a number of operations.
First you go and retrieve these and then
like do this do that or whatever is that
right? So that is all a task. It is not
the individual operations. So open AP
specific specification uh it meant for
operation not for a task. While you can
also do a task I'm not saying like with
open AP specification you cannot do a
task but the main purpose of open AP
specification it's to cover the
individual operations. So having said
that there are quite a few problems that
we have with open AP specification
especially when you try to integrate
with LLM. So if you see here this
particular op AP specification so it is
not greatly detailed enough for LLM to
understand. So here it says that the
verb it's get verb and this is the path
it takes a ID. So LLM might not even
know like what exactly this is and like
it look for the parameters right. So it
is not greatly detailed enough. However,
like if you see the MCP equivalent, uh
it has all this information name aligns
with the description and like it clearly
says that hey like what exactly the
input I'm looking for what is needed and
all of those right
and uh then likewise like open AP
specification it's meant for HTTP only
LLM
might use HTTP or any other uh you know
mode of uh communicating right uh Q uh
SSC anything. So, not necessarily the
HTTP verb, HTTP protocol, but then like
there are plenty of other ways to
interact with the LLM, right? LLM and
the client. Then we have a no guarantee
for LLM tool safety. So basically like
with this definition, so let's assume
that you want to delete something.
Before you delete something, you want to
get the permission, right? So again like
it's a two different actions like first
you need to get the approval and like
you perform the action. So in MCP you
can clearly see that hey like whenever
you have a safety profile you have to
first you know complete that exercise
before you actually do that that can be
done and then like if you see here open
API specification uh will have lot of
these individual operations so that's
what uh you know I I mentioned right so
it will have lots and lots of individual
operations uh however like when you come
to the MC uh the LLM uh you don't need
lot of operation you need to have a uh
task. So that's what we will do it with
the MCP where one open API
endpoint with the MCP implementation. So
if you see here here I'm saying like a
get uh this is the endpoint and like it
takes this particular parameter. So if
you do the same thing in MCP it will be
something of this sort. So get the
customer details. There is going to be a
description that LLM can understand. It
is going to have the uh required this is
what it is needed and um you know of
type whatever is the train. So the LLM
can clearly understand the operation and
what exactly it takes what is the intent
of this operation. So that's what the
LLM needs to know. Now with that
understanding let's go to the MCP and
try to understand the components or a
primitives right. So first we will have
a tools or a verb. Uh so whenever you
want to perform a action you will be
defining a tool. Then uh you will have a
prompt. Uh so you can also attach the
prompt as a part of MCP so that whoever
is going to use your MCP they can also
can you know use your prompt rather than
they try to figure out the prompt. You
can built in your prompt as a part of
MCP and send it to them. Also, you can
attach some resources that you think
it's needed for your MCP to work
properly. So, for the first demo, I will
be using this particular uh MCP
implementation. So, it's called MCP
server calculator. So, this is a you
know pretty simple implementation. The
way you use it's a UVX and then like a
name of the uh MCP server. And if you go
to the code uh it's pretty simple. So if
you just go to the calculator py all
they do is that they just defined one uh
you know calculate method and then like
you know some implementation it's here
and they have a test and they have a uh
toml file here. So we already discussed
how do we package the python uh so you
like they they packaged everything and
published. So this is what we will be
using. Now let's go to the visual studio
code. So what I want to do is that I
want to use the MCP server calculator
that we discussed. It involves three
different steps. First you have to
import the tool. Then you have to
initialize the tool. So here like if you
see like we are using the MCP studio
tool with the command uvx and the like
name of the MCP server it's server MCP
server calculator.
Then when you define the agent uh you
need to just say that hey like you need
to use the MCP tool but like you have to
provide the MCP tool in the tools
section with that let me go ahead and
run the program. As you see here like a
user pro query it's already provided
here. So the program will not ask for a
user input. So now let me go and run the
program. So this is going to be 24. So
there are few things that we need to
understand. First if you see here first
it is making a call to list tools
request uh list prompt request. What it
will do is that it will go to the MCP
server and ask for the list of tools
available and uh ask for list of prompts
available as a part of MCP server. Now
user query it's provided. Now it is
making the first call. It is doing the
uh multiplication.
Then it will be performing the addition.
says that I will use the calculator to
perform the addition and it is making a
call. Then finally like we have the
result. So this is how the MCP server uh
can be used. Now we will try to
understand the type of tools right. So I
said like we are using the MCP studio
tool. Let's go back and try to
understand the different type of tools.
So if you see here first we have a MCP
studio tool. So whenever you have a MCP
installed server installed and running
in your local machine you can use the
MCP studio tool basically like it's a
standard input output right so you will
have everything in the same machine so
there is you know the MCP client doesn't
have to use a different protocol it can
directly use the input uh output to
connect with your MCP server and this is
what typically we will be using for
development purposes then we have a MCP
streamable HTTP protocol
So let's assume that you wanted to
consume the MCP. However, like it is
hosted on a remote machine, then you can
use you have to use the uh streamable
HTTP protocol to connect with that. Say
like you wanted to make use of Google's
MCP or Facebook's MCP then most likely
it is going to be the streamable HTTP
protocol, right? Then uh the other other
one it's the websocket protocol. So
let's assume that uh so the difference
between studio uh uh streamable uh
compared to the MCP uh websocket
protocol is that websocket protocol it's
meant for a two-way communication or
birectional communication. So whenever
you wanted to send the log or high
frequency of a data uh to your MCP then
you will be using the web socket
protocol. And how do we use each of
these? So if you just come over here uh
here we say like uh you know uh MCP
studio tool provide a name and commands
arguments pass it then you will use it
right. Then for the streamable HTTP
pretty same again like a streamable HTTP
protocol name URL instead of the
commands you will be passing the URL
authorization you will be providing all
of these information here. Uh streamable
so it will be using the uh WSS protocol.
So we will be passing that name and the
WSS protocol that you will be passing
it. Now we will also try to understand
the architecture. So if you see here the
MCP client in this case like the program
that runs our uh LLM, right? So that is
going to be the client application. So
think of this way you have a front- end
application.
It can be your you know uh web
application or your IDE or anything that
will make use of your application the
LLM application that you are building
the LLM application now consider as a
MCP client application not your web
application or IDE but the application
that runs your LLM code it's the MCP
client the MCP client will talk to the
MCP server to get to know the tools
information say like you want to perform
some Google operation Google drive
operation or YouTube operation. So there
is going to be a corresponding MCP
server that your uh application like
your LLM application need to interact
with. So it will connect through either
of these. It will either use the HTDIO
or a HTTP or a websocket protocol.
Right?
selection again I said like when you're
really building a local development you
will be using the std but when you are
like it if MCP it's hosted outside
remote then you will be using the uh
streamable HTTP for a high frequency
connection you will be using the
websocket right so now with that
understanding let's go back and see like
how do we implement our own MCP server
let's go to the visual studio and try to
understand that let me go ahead and
clear the console
So if you see here not in this
particular program we are just using a
single MCP server but at times we wanted
to use multiple MCP server. So if you
see here I'm using the know exact MCP
server calculator and I'm also using the
server time. So in this particular
program I will be showcasing how do we
use multiple MCP servers. So everything
going to be same except that we define
two different MCP servers here and like
in the tools section we provide both the
names that's it then the user will be
asking okay what is the you know
calculated value for this and like what
is the time in Tokyo now if you see here
it involves two different tools for this
one we will be using the calculator tool
and for this we will be using the time
tool so now let me go ahead and run this
program this is going to be 25th 5th.
Now let's go ahead and run. So as you
see here, first it used the calculator
tool to perform this calculation. Then
it used the time tool to perform uh the
time retrieval. This is how you can use
multiple MCP servers. Now let's see how
do we build our own MCP server. I'm not
going to create a package rather it is
going to be a simple implementation. And
if you want to package it, I have a
video that showcases how do we package
the Python. uh but let me go ahead and
open this particular program. So first
we have to create a MCP server right. So
in this case I will be using the uh fast
MCP. However there are multiple
frameworks are available. Let me go
ahead and show you. So if you're coming
from Python most likely we will be using
the fast MCP. However, like for
Typescript, you have a MCP SDK and uh
say like you have a open API
implementation uh then you you can
directly use uh speak easy that will
convert your open API uh rather than
like rewriting everything right so you
can very well use uh uh speak easy and
uh if you're coming from go you can use
foxy so which one to choose it it really
depends so if you are starting with
python you will be using python uh fast
MCP but you uh if you have a rest
existing rest endpoint then you can use
uh speak easyc uh if you have a you know
uh go implementation or high performance
requirement that then most likely we'll
be going with foxy now let's go back so
if you look into this implementation it
is pretty simple first you have to
define this fast mcp provide a name and
like if there are any dependencies you
have to provide that dependency as well
then You can define the tool using mcpto
tool. Here like if you see like I have
defined a method called calculate mean
that takes a you know list of float and
you know does the calculation and I also
have some prompt. So prompt you can
define by uh using uh the decorator
mcp.prompt you will provide the prompt
here. So it is going to return that then
you can run this. If you're running it
from directly then this particular
method will get called. But what I want
to do is that I want to use the uh MCP
studio tool. So if you see here the name
of this particular implement MCP server
it's a calculator and the command it's
python and like this is what it is going
to run. So that is just the name of my
python program and like it is going to
use this argument as well. Now in this
program we are trying to get the prompt
as well as we are trying to use the
tool. So if you see here like as we have
defined the MCP server as MCP- server we
can use the get prompt uh method to get
the prompt and the name of the prompt if
you go back and see like this is the
name of that uh definition right so all
you need to do is that get prompt you
just need to provide the name of the
definition get the instruction and if
you see here like we are using that
prompt for your agent so like the again
the prompt by itself it's defined in the
MCP we are getting the prompt using the
get prompt by passing the uh name of
that prompt and like using that prompt
as a system instruction for our agent.
Now again like uh the tool uh as we
discussed earlier we will be passing
EMCP server as a tool here. Now let me
go ahead and run the program. If you
look into the query it says that analyze
the weekly server latency whatever is
that some data set it's provided. So now
let me clear the console. Now let me go
and run this program. Let me go ahead
and run that.
So let me expand this guy. So if you see
here, it is running the MCP server using
the stdio and it is getting the uh tools
and the prompt and it is getting the
prompt because like I have used the
prompt, right? And like I am printing
the prompt. So this is exactly the same
thing, right? So this is exactly same
thing as we are getting the prompt, I'm
also printing that. So this is exactly
the same thing. This will be used for
our system instruction. Now we are
passing this user query analyze the
weekly uh you know server latency or
whatever is that. Now if you just come
over here it is making a call and like
it is calculating the mean. If you go to
the program exactly you will see the
same uh logging information here. So
calculating mean for data whatever is
that. So calculating mean for data
whatever is that and like the mean it's
calculated. So now it will be using the
prompt uh you know as we are using the
prompt as a system prompt it will be
using the same prompt and it will be
displaying the information. So like this
you can define your tools and prompts uh
using the MCP. Now let me go and so this
time around we have used std IO to run
our MCP. Now we can also use a HTTP. So
now let me go ahead and open the HTTP.
So like if you just come over here, this
is exactly the same program except that
I do not have the prompt because like we
know that prompt is also going to work.
Uh that is not the main thing that I'm
trying to showcase. I'm just trying to
showcase a different protocols that can
be used with MCP. So this time around we
are not going to use the SDIO rather
like we will be using the HTTP and the
HTTP will be running in the port uh
8,000. As you see here, this will be
running in 8,000. Now let me go down and
open new terminal and the uh let me try
to run that that is going to be 27.
Now let me run it. So now the HTT MCP
server it's started and it is using the
port uh 8,000. Now let me go to the
terminal here again. Let me clear this.
Now if I just come over here this is
going to be the same right? If you see
here this time around I am using the MCP
streamable HTTP because like I'm using
the HTTP based uh transport here and uh
name is going to be the same calculator
and like this time around I will be
using the URL and I don't have any
headers because like right now like this
particular implementation doesn't
support any authentication that's it
like rest of the things will be seen. Uh
so I'll be asking okay what is the uh
mean for this number. So now let me go
ahead and run this. So now as you see
here to find the mean of this particular
number I have used the calculator tool
and whatever is that now you see all
this information here right now if you
just come over here how do I know this
uses my tool right so if you just come
over here you will see all the
processing information first the client
requested the server for a tool
information prompt information then you
see that the uh you know calculating
mean for data whatever is that because
that is what we have here right so
calculating mean for data. So it
actually uses my MCP server to do the
calculation. Right? So this is how you
can use uh MCP for your local
development using HDDIO transport and
like for remote deployment you can use
HTTP. So far in this video we discussed
a lot about MCP. What is MCP and how do
we use the external MCP and how do we
build our own MCP? How do we deploy our
MCP? All these things we discussed in
this video. In the next video we will be
discussing about the workflow especially
the executors.